Robert Orben Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Alphabetical File, 1941-2019 (Box 3-32)
  - Schlesinger, Robert, 2006-2007 (Box 27)
  - Scott, Mike, and Sheila Scott, 1979, 1989-1992, 2000-2002 (Box 27)
  - Seattle Post-Intelligencer, 1981-1983 (Box 27)
  - Seplin, Amy, 1996 (Box 27)
  - Shafer, Ronald G., 1976-1980, 1989-2001, (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - Shapiro, Irv, 1978-1979 (Box 28)
  - Shearer, Lloyd, 1971, 1993-2001 (Box 28)
  - Shell Oil Co., 1976 (Box 28)
  - Shields, Mark, 1981-1982 (Box 28)
  - Sidey, Hugh, 1995-1997 (Box 28)
  - Simon, Neil, 1994-1995 (Box 28)
  - Sites, James N., 1988, 1999-2015 (Box 28)
  - Skelton, Red, 1965, 1971, 1983, 1990-1991, 1998 (Box 28)
  - Speakers bureaus, miscellaneous, 1977-1995, (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Speaking, correspondence, 1973-1981, (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Speaking and writing fee quotes, 1977-1985, (3 folders) (Box 28)
  - Speaking and writing fee quotes, 1986-1994, (3 folders) (Box 29)
  - Speaking possibilities, 1971-1981 (Box 29)
  - Speech book, undated (Box 29)
  - Speech Communications Association, 1981 (Box 29)
  - Speechwriter's Newsletter, 1980-1989, 1995 (Box 29)
  - Stalter, J. Neil, 1997 (Box 29)
  - Steiner, Paul, 1985 (Box 29)
  - Stessin, Larry, 1994 (Box 29)
  - Success Unlimited magazine, 1979 (Box 29)
  - Sweet, Cody, 1972-1978 (Box 29)
  - Tannen, Louis, 1951-1961 (Box 29)
  - Technique book, 1956-1977, (2 folders) (Box 29)
  - Technique book, 1956-1977, (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - Teller, Sanford, 1975-1976, 1990 (Box 30)
  - Theis, Paul A., 1971-1974, 1981, 1992, 2004 (Box 30)
  - Thomas, Lowell, 1975-1991 (Box 30)
  - Thought control, 1941-1943, 1993 (Box 30)
  - Trachtenberg, Stephen Joel, 1987-1988, 1999 (Box 30)
  - Trimark Publishing Co., 1987-1995, (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - True, Herb, 1969-1983, 1990-1991, 1997-1999, (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - Trujillo, Marilyn, 1998-2006 (Box 31)
  - Turner, Morrie, 1965, 2000, undated (Box 31)
  - Unitarian humor, 1963-circa 1975 (Box 31)
  - University of Wyoming, Laramie, Wyo. 1981-1988 (Box 31)
  - Vallée, Rudy, 1964, 1971-1975, 1982-1986 (Box 31)
  - Wade, Mark, 1986 (Box 31)
  - Walker & Associates, 1988-1993 (Box 31)
  - Wall, Thomas J., 1993-1995 (Box 31)
  - Walters, Dottie, 1981-1988, 1994, 2000 (Box 31)
  - Ward, Tom, 1971 (Box 31)
  - Washington Press Club Foundation, 1988 (Box 31)
  - We the People 200, Philadelphia, Pa., 1987 (Box 31)
  - White, Daniel R., 1991-1993 (Box 31)
  - Wightman, Tony, 1989 (Box 31)
  - Williams, Pat, 1984, 1995, 2002-2003, (2 folders) (Box 31)
  - Wiltshire Book Co., 1990-1995, 2006 (Box 32)
  - Woloshin, Douglas, 1980-1981, 1993 (Box 32)
  - Workman, Peter, 1966, 1977-1982, 1989, 2002-2005 (Box 32)
  - Workshop Library on World Humour, 1973, 1987 (Box 32)
  - Writer's Digest magazine, 1970, 1981 (Box 32)
  - Writers Guild of America, 1962-1975, 1985, 1997 (Box 32)
- Speeches and Writings, 1945-2018 (Box 32-49)
  The Speeches and Writings series contains approximately sixty years of jokes, one-liners, writings, and remarks from Orben's career as a comedy writer and humor consultant for performers, television programs, public figures, and corporate clients. His earliest material is included in a grouping of small self-published books, such as The Encyclopedia of Patter (1946), Magicdotes (1948), and The Working Comedian’s Gag File (1956), that Orben wrote for magicians, emcees, comedians, and other performers. The largest portion of this material relates to his topical humor service, Orben’s Current Comedy, that he edited from 1958 to 1989 with a small break between 1968 and 1971. This periodical, issued monthly and then bi-monthly, contains jokes and one-liners relating to current events and prominent figures in politics and entertainment. Orben later compiled some of this material into a series of books. Orben’s writing for television is documented in an index card file arranged by topic, labeled “Skelton Stockpile,” containing jokes he wrote for The Red Skelton Hour as well material he wrote for The Jack Paar Program in 1962. Another set of index cards contains material Orben wrote for comedian Dick Gregory’s book, From the Back of the Bus (1962). Additional material relating to this project can be found in the Alphabetical File series. Another group of writings contains material he wrote for International Business Machines Corporation (IBM) corporate events. Orben’s articles and essays about the writing, effective delivery, and use of humor in speeches, as well as his speeches and speech material about humor in the presidency are also included in this series. An unpublished memoir offers Orben’s account of events in his life until the end of his time in the Gerald R. Ford administration. Additional jokes that he sent to individuals and publications, particularly topical material written in the 1990s, are located in the Alphabetical File series under the name of the person or publication.
  Material types include jokes, articles, books, book drafts, periodicals, a memoir, notes, interview transcripts, speeches, and scripts.
  Arranged alphabetically by title or type of material and therein chronologically. The file structure of the digital content maintained as received.
  - Articles and essays, 1945-1946, 1968-1972, 1978-2002, (3 folders) (Box 32)
  - "Bob Orben's Current Comedy for Speakers," American Speaker magazine, 1994-2006, (3 folders) (Box 32)
  - "Bob Orben's Current Comedy for Speakers," American Speaker magazine, 2007-2009 (Box 33)
  - Book drafts, 1990-circa 2000, (2 folders) (Box 33)
  - Book drafts, undated, (2 folders) (Box 33)
  - Book drafts, undated, (3 folders) (Box 34)
  - Book material, 1971-circa 1999, (5 folders) (Box 35)
  - Book material, 1971-circa 1999, (2 folders) (Box 36)
  - Books, 1946-1951, (5 folders) (Box 36)
  - Books, 1952-1956, (6 folders) (Box 37)
  - Books, 1957-1964, (7 folders) (Box 38)
  - Gregory, Dick, book material, circa 1962 See Oversize (Box OV 2)
  - "Hot Lines" column material, circa 1968 See Oversize (Box OV 3)
  - Humorous quotes in print, 1995-2018 (Box 39)
  - International Business Machines Corp. (IBM) material, 1977-1980, (11 folders) (Box 39)
  - International Business Machines Corp. (IBM) material, 1981-1984, (10 folders) (Box 40)
  - International Business Machines Corp. (IBM) material, 1985-1986, (7 folders) (Box 41)
  - International Business Machines Corp. (IBM) material, undated (Box 41)
  - International Business Machines Corp. (IBM) material, undated, (3 folders) (Box 42)
  - Interviews with Orben (Box 42)
    - Gerald R. Ford Oral History Project, 2008-2009 (Box 42)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1983, 1999-2013 (Box 42)
    - Miscellaneous, audio file, 2000, mss86325_201_004
    - Miscellaneous, video file, 2012, mss86325_201_003
  - Jack Paar Program material, 1962 (Box 42)
  - Lewis, Shari, material, 1968 (Box 42)
  - Magic periodicals, 1946 (Box 42)
  - Memoir, circa 1993-circa 1994, (3 folders) (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous jokes, 1960s-1998, undated, (7 folders) (Box 43)
  - Miscellaneous jokes, undated See Oversize (Box OV 4)
  - Miscellaneous jokes, undated See Oversize (Box OV 5)
  - Miscellaneous writings, 2011-2014, undated (Box 44)
  - Notes and jottings, 1972-2017, undated, (4 folders) (Box 44)
  - Orben Comedy Letter, 1971-1972 (Box 44)
  - Orben's Comedy Fillers, 1971-1980, (2 folders) (Box 44)
  - Orben's Current Comedy (Box 45)
    - Issues, bound (Box 45)
      - Vol. 1, 1958, Nov.-1959, Oct. (Box 45)
      - Vol. 2, 1959, Nov.-1960, Oct. (Box 45)
      - Vol. 3, 1960, Nov.-1961, Oct. (Box 45)
      - Vol. 4, 1961, Nov.-1962, Oct. (Box 45)
      - Vol. 5, 1962, Nov.-1963, Oct. (Box 45)
      - Vol. 6, 1963, Nov.-1964, Oct. (Box 45)
      - Vol. 7, 1964, Nov.-1965, Oct. (Box 45)
      - Vol. 8, 1965, Nov.-1966, Oct. (Box 45)
      - Vol. 9, 1966, Nov.-1967, Sept. (Box 46)
      - Vol. 10, 1967, Oct.-1968, Apr. (Box 46)
    - Issues, unbound (Box 46)
      - Nos. 190-242, 1971-1972 (Box 46)
      - Nos. 243-292, 1973-1974 (Box 46)
      - Nos. 293-340, 1975-1976 (Box 46)
      - Nos. 341-388, 1977-1978 (Box 46)
      - Nos. 389-436, 1979-1980 (Box 47)
      - Nos. 437-484, 1981-1982 (Box 47)
      - Nos. 485-532, 1983-1984 (Box 47)
      - Nos. 533-580, 1985-1986 (Box 47)
      - Nos. 581-628, 1987-1988 (Box 47)
      - Nos. 629-630, 1989 (Box 47)
    - Material by contributors, undated See Oversize (Box OV 6)
    - Unpublished, new material, undated See Oversize (Box OV 7)
    - Unpublished, new material, undated See Oversize (Box OV 8)
    - Unpublished, new material, undated See Oversize (Box OV 9)
    - Unpublished, new material, undated See Oversize (Box OV 10)
  - Red Skelton Hour (Box OV 11- OV 14)
    - Miscellaneous material, 1964-1968, 1977 See Oversize (Box OV 11)
    - "Skelton Stockpile" topical file, circa 1964-1969 See Oversize (Box OV 12)
    - "Skelton Stockpile" topical file, circa 1964-1969 See Oversize (Box OV 13)
    - "Skelton Stockpile" topical file, circa 1964-1969 See Oversize (Box OV 14)
  - Speech pages, 1970s-2000s, (3 folders) (Box 48)
  - Speeches, 1970s, (4 folders) (Box 48)
  - Speeches, 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 49)
  - Speeches, 1980s-2013, (5 folders) (Box 49)
  - Speeches, video file, 2013, mss86325_201_006
- Miscellany, 1945-2019 (Box 50-52)
  A small Miscellany series contains additional material documenting Orben's life and career including press clippings about or mentioning him and photographs depicting his work with President Gerald R. Ford. A scrapbook contains Orben's earliest published writings, most of which relate to magic.
  Material types include card files, calendars, photographs, press clippings, lists, passports, a scrapbook, and video files from an award ceremony.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material or name. The file structure of the digital content maintained as received.
  - Address file (Box OV 15 - OV 16)
    - A-L, undated See Oversize (Box OV 15)
    - M-Y, undated See Oversize (Box OV 16)
  - Biographical information, circa 1970s, 1990, circa 2007, 2015 (Box 50)
  - Calendars, 1976-1977 (Box 50)
  - Christmas cards, 2007, undated (Box 50)
  - Drawing of Orben, 1987 (Box 50)
  - Honors and awards, 1975-1979, 1992, 2013 (Box 50)
  - Honors and awards, video file, 2013, mss86325_201_005
  - Lists, 1969-2013, (2 folders) (Box 50)
  - Orben, Jean (Box 50)
    - Notes, 1995-2016, undated (Box 50)
    - Passports, 1964-1985 (Box 50)
  - Passports, 1964-1985 (Box 51)
  - Photographs (Box 51)
    - Portraits, 1950s-1980s, (2 folders) (Box 51)
    - Various events, 1973-1986, 2004, undated (Box 51)
    - White House, 1974-1976 See also Oversize, (4 folders) (Box 51)
  - Press clippings, 1954-1957, 1963-2019, (3 folders) (Box 52)
  - Printed matter, 1972-2016 (Box 52)
  - Scrapbook, 1945-1947 See Oversize (Box OV 17)
- Oversize, 1945-1977 (Box OV 1-OV 17)
  Card files of jokes, card files of addresses, photographs, a proclamation, and a scrapbook.
  Listed and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the material was separated. The items are physically grouped and arranged by size.
  - Alphabetical File
    - Bicentennial proclamation and photo collage, 1976, (Container 13, White House memorabilia) (Box OV 1)
  - Speeches and Writings
    - Card file, material written for Dick Gregory's books, circa 1962 (Box OV 2)
    - Card file, "Hot Lines" column material, circa 1968 (Box OV 3)
    - Card file, miscellaneous jokes, undated (Box OV 4)
    - Card file, miscellaneous jokes, undated (Box OV 5)
    - Orben's Current Comedy
      - Card file, material by contributors, undated (Box OV 6)
      - Card file, unpublished, new material, undated (Box OV 7)
      - Card file, unpublished, new material, undated (Box OV 8)
      - Card file, unpublished, new material, undated (Box OV 9)
      - Card file, unpublished, new material, undated (Box OV 10)
    - Red Skelton Hour
      - Card file, miscellaneous material, 1964-1968, 1977 (Box OV 11)
      - Card file, "Skelton Stockpile" topical file, circa 1964-1969 (Box OV 12)
      - Card file, "Skelton Stockpile" topical file, circa 1964-1969 (Box OV 13)
      - Card file, "Skelton Stockpile" topical file, circa 1964-1969 (Box OV 14)
  - Miscellany
    - Card file, address file, A-L, undated (Box OV 15)
    - Card file, address file, M-Y, undated (Box OV 16)
    - Photographs, White House, 1974-1976, (Container 51, same heading) (Box OV 1)
    - Scrapbook, clippings by and about Robert Orben and Jean Orben, 1945-1947 (Box OV 17)